[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
today I want to do two
things one is to discuss geodesics a
little
more and to explain a little more
thoroughly the connection between
gravitational
forces and
geodesics or the motion of geodesics uh
through space time so for the first part
of the lecture tonight we're going to be
thinking about space time not just space
but
SpaceTime but the mathematics for
SpaceTime is very
similar to the mathematics for ordinary
space there's also a metric
when we're talking about space and time
instead of using M and N for indices we
use Greek indices mu and
new and again there's a notion of
distance which is called proper
time I also write it well I guess I
usually write it uh I I have trouble
keeping my notations in entirely
consistent I'll try to keep them
consistent as I can instead of calling
it d s
squared uh s is usually the label for
distance in space one calls it D Squared
because it's more like time proper time
the proper time along a
trajectory as a little interval along
the
trajectory it has a set of differential
display ments which are called DX
mu remember mu
runs from 0 1 2 and
3 1 2 and three represent space zero
represents
time
and the square of the proper time along
a little interval like that is defined
again in terms of a
metric in general this metric in special
relativity in special relativity this
metric is
constant everywhere is the same and it's
usually taken to
be the symbol atam muu atam muu is the
analog for SpaceTime of the chronica
Delta symbol Delta munu Delta MN for
ordinary space and it's given not by 1
one one
one it's a 4x4
Matrix but it's given by one 0 0 0 0 -
1 0 0 0 0 - 1 0 0 0 0 - 1
all right so in other words it's of the
form dt^ 2 minus if you if we wanted to
replace these by
T X Y and
Z then in special relativity the metric
here would just be D to squared or the
uh proper time would just be dt^ 2 which
is equal to dt^ 2 minus dx^ 2 - D y^ 2us
dz^2
that would be the rule in units in which
the speed of light is equal to
one where would I put the where would
where would I put the speed of light if
I wanted to include it in this
formula
well if I wanted to which is called
proper time to have units of time not of
space but of time
then I wouldn't want to put the speed of
light in front of dt^ s because the
speed of light has units what is those
units units is units of velocity
kilometers per second but the place that
it would go would be in here over c
squared
uh plus like that all right so um notice
first of
all that if the speed of light is large
which it is in ordinary
units in ordinary units where the speed
of light is large now what does it mean
to say the speed of light is large the
speed of light is the speed of light
it's neither large nor small it is what
it is what it really means is that the
things that we're interested in are
moving very slowly with respect to the
speed of light so that uh so that we can
think of the speed of light as much
faster than anything we might be
interested in under those
circumstances if this object here is
moving
slowly
then uh then we can treat the speed of
light as being very large and this piece
here is essentially
negligible and D tow is the same as DT
so for slowly moving
objects in a frame of
reference which uh in a frame of
reference in which everything is moving
slow
slowly then time and proper time are
very close to being the same
thing but more generally if if we're
interested in things which are moving
fast then this is the proper time along
a trajectory it's the time as recorded
by a clock moving with the
object a standard clock made in the
standard clock Factory moving with the
object will record proper time not
coordinate time this would be called
proper time now in general theory of
relativity general theory of relativity
is related to special relativity in the
same way that flat space is related to
curved space we haven't discussed yet
what curvature means we're going to do
that
tonight but
um yeah I have a question isn't DT the
one that the clock would record if it's
moving with the object no DT is the one
that the clock
records the clock moves and ticks off
proper time in the same way that if you
have a curve in space and you lay out a
tape measure along it the tape measure
doesn't
record y or X it records distance along
the
curve all right think of the clock
moving with the object as a kind of
SpaceTime tape measure keeping track of
proper time along the
trajectory each tick of the clock can be
thought of as a marker along this
fictitious tape measure the SpaceTime
tape measure the only peculiar thing is
that there's a sign in here all right so
that we need to keep track
of but as I
said uh general relativity is related to
special relativity in exactly the same
way or exactly in an analogous way to
the way that flat space that would be
flat space would be like special
relativity and curved space would be
like general relativity except it's
curved
SpaceTime other than that the
rules are basically the
same for
geometry uh the existence of a metric
the notion of covariant derivative
exactly the same the christopal symbols
are made up out of
the metric tensor the metric tensor is a
tensor there
are covariant contravariant
uh
tensors covariant
derivatives christopal symbols and
they're all made exactly the same
way uh as they would be in space except
that you use the SpaceTime metric rather
than the space metric by
itself notice there's one time
Direction One Direction with a plus sign
and all the others have a minus sign
okay no this is last week quick quick
question yeah
the Matrix size whether it's four or
five or six is is this what accounts for
the extra dimensions in string
theory uh yes yes the number of x's and
the size of the Matrix is related not
just related to is exactly as you say
the uh the number of Dimensions doesn't
have to be String Theory whatever
whatever SpaceTime we're talking about
the dimensionality is just the number of
uh entries here and it's also the size
of the matrices but you know apart from
that the rules are basically the same in
every Dimension and uh whether it's
space time or just plain
space all right
now excuse me
when we're dealing with flat space or
SpaceTime we don't ever really need to
introduce curvy linear
coordinates we may or may not want to in
fact it almost seems like a stupid thing
to do because it's going to complicate
the description of
things when do we do it and why do we do
it well we do it because we're sometimes
interested in accelerated frames of
reference an accelerated frame of
reference is basically one in which the
coordinate uh coordinates of space are
being
accelerated uh let's say they start
coming in from the left and run off to
the right you know what I
mean and the mathematical description of
an accelerated frame of
reference uh in terms of an original
unac what's an unaccelerated frame of
reference called an inertial frame yeah
the description of an accelerated frame
in Newtonian mechanics we get relativity
for a minute in Newtonian mechanics is
just a frame of reference well let's see
if we have our inertial frame of
reference
TX that's our inertial frame of
reference in this frame of reference all
objects Move Along straight lines then
the accelerated frame of reference is
one whose
coordinates are curved like
this they form
hyperboloids and in this frame of
reference an object an object which is
moving in along a straight line in XT
coordinates would in fact not be moving
along a linear trajectory in the new
coordinates
and so it appears to be accelerated of
course the object is simply accelerated
with the equal and opposite acceleration
to the way the coordinate frame is being
accelerated it's just the old elevator
story uh and had it not been for
Einstein thinking about elevators and
acceleration and its relationship to
gravity nobody would have been stupid
enough to introduce curved coordinates
into physics why would you do such a
foolish thing it makes things more
complicated
ated and of course the answer was the
equivalence principle the curved
coordinates are the same as a
gravitational field
now
uh so we do introduce curved
coordinates that itself is not the same
as space-time curvature we'll come to
it but once we introduce curved
coordinates and so forth the whole
apparatus of tensor analysis
transformations of things from one frame
of reference to another all of that uh
gets inherited from the geometry of
space that we've discussed up till
now all right let's see I'm not sure
what order to go in I think we'll begin
with
curvature I
had or should we begin with geodesics
take a vote who wants geodesics who
wants
curvature all right we hear curvature
okay so I'm not even sure why I talked
about this all right we come back to it
we'll come back to
it oh yeah I do
remember yeah curved coordinates are
sort of a luxury that you can use or not
use in special uh in special
relativity but they're not a luxury when
you come to think about
gravity uh if you well in the general
theory of relativity but in particular
even in Newtonian
gravity it's not possible to remove a
real gravitational field by changing
coordinates one of these fake
gravitational fields which is just due
to accelerated coordinates that can be
removed by just replacing the The
Accelerated coordinates by non-
accelerated coordinates but a real
gravitational field you cannot remove
that way uh for example if you have a
star and there's a gravitational field
pulling you toward the star then in a
small elevator over here you might be
able to remove the effects of the
gravitational field by just letting the
small elevator freely fall and then all
experiments inside the uh uh the falling
elevator would be exactly as if there
was no gravitational field and that's
not quite true it's not quite true
because of tidal forces because across
the elevator the gravitational field
varies a little bit there's a little bit
of tidal forces but if you make the
elevator small enough so that the
gravitational field doesn't vary very
much then you completely remove the
effects of gravity inside that
elevator by just letting the elevator
fall well that's like kind of
introducing a coordinate frame inside
the elevator which is like the straight
line which is like the um the inertial
frame and the coordinates which are not
falling those are like the curved
coordinates you can't however get rid of
the curved coordinates or the
gravitational field everywhere simultan
mously there's an
obstruction if you introduce an
acceleration vertically that's not going
to get rid of the gravitational field
over here or over here if you introduce
a coordinate system which is
accelerating vertically let's say in the
down Direction that's only going to make
things worse over here it might remove
the gravitational field in the falling
accelerator on this side falling um uh
elevator on this side
but the same coordinate transformation
will only
increase the gravitational field down
here so there's an
obstruction uh to
removing the effects of gravity or an
obstruction to finding
coordinates which sort of straighten out
all the effects of gravity and get rid
of
them that
obstruction mathematically is the same
obstruction
as the
obstruction of taking a general space or
general space time and thinking of it as
flat first of all what does it mean for
a space or A Spacetime to be flat in the
case of a space it means that you can
find coordinates it doesn't mean that
every coordinate system has its property
it means you can find
coordinates which have the property
that the metric tensor is just Delta
MN more specifically it really doesn't
need to be Delta MN the metric is
constant in
space
incidentally there
are coordinates in which the metric is
constant in space but which in which
it's not Delta MN if you choose
coordinates which are at Angles like
that on this
Blackboard uh but which are completely
uniform made up out of straight lines
equally spaced then the metric is not
Delta MN it's some other numerical
tensor like this but it's constant from
point to point so another way of saying
it is that a flat SpaceTime is one in
which the metric can be chosen to be
absolutely constant
everywhere okay to put it slightly
differently the metric can be chosen so
that the derivative of the
metric with respect to
coordinates notice this is the thing
with three indices the general
derivative of the metric with respect to
position can be chosen to be equal to
zero you can find a metric you can find
a coordinate transformation
which will make the derivatives of the
metric all equal to zero that is a flat
SpaceTime by
definition okay one all right now I
assert not only I assert I will give you
an
argument that you can always at a
particular Point here's here's some
curved space a general
space without even knowing what
curvature means I will tell you right
now that it is always possible at a
particular specific point to choose
coordinates to choose coordinates so
that at any specific point the
derivatives of the metric equal zero
that's always possible to do let's see
how we can uh argue that that there's in
other words there's enough freedom in
the choice of
coordinates so that one point you can
choose G to have derivatives equal to
zero in every
direction first derivative the first
derivative not the second derivative and
the third derivative and the fourth
derivative but that the first derivative
of G can be chosen to be zero at a
point let's figure out how many
equations and how many unknowns there
are supposing we have some
coordinates let's call them
x coordinates in
which the metric is not constant or does
have uh derivatives at this point in
other words where the G's are not
without derivative at this point and
let's make a coordinate transformation
to a new set of coordinates I'm going to
call them
y I'm going to choose the origin of the
y-coordinates to be exactly the same as
the origin of the X x
coordinates all right for example a
simple example would be ym equals
XM that's a dumb coordinate
transformation it's no coordinate
transformation at all but now I want to
make it more General in that and I'm
going to assume that we can tailor
series expand that we can expand y's and
x uh that we can start with ym = XM Plus
a
deviation which is going to be quadratic
and then of course there can be cubic
terms higher terms than that but let's
add in some uh some quadratic terms and
the quadratic terms will be quadratic in
X the left hand side has an index M
associated with it so we better put here
some coefficients these are numerical
coefficients just numbers at the the
moment they're not even functions
because we're just interested in one
particular point at one particular point
we'll add in and I'm going to put a
CM
RS
xrxs this is the most General thing that
I can write down which is
quadratic in the x's and of
course has an index
M from here and XR an RNs that combine
with the X's here that's in fact the
most General coordinate transformation
which is quadratic in the x's and which
has the property that the origin of
coordinates namely yal 0 is the same as
xal Z all right x equals 0 and Y equals
0 the same all right so all that means
I've just introduced other
coordinates
located with the same origin over here
but they're curved relative to the X's
that they're curved has to do with this
term here relative to the X's okay how
how many how many variables do I have to
play with in making such Transformations
let's let's figure out how many such
variables are there question it looks as
if if you're saying that's like a tailor
expansion look like you've almost
assumed did you drop out um the first
derivative or I guess you you didn't oh
that's actually here okay and I could
have made it a little more General in
this but I just uh decided that the
leading term would be Y is equal to X
all right the leading term y equal to I
could have made it more complicated so
that the linear term here was a little
more complicated but there's no need to
do so all right so how many constants C
are there just for fun let's see how
many there are C let's forget the M for
a minute and just think of CRS for fixed
m c is a matrix just putting our hand
over M here C is a matrix and
furthermore it can be taken to be a
symmetric Matrix it can be a symmetric
Matrix because there's no difference
between XR * Xs and Xs *
XR so C is symmetric with respect to
Interchange of R and S or can be chosen
to be
so uh if we have a space with a certain
number of Dimensions like say d
dimensions then how many independent
entries are there for a symmetric
Matrix no no D Dimensions six is six is
right in three dimensions D * d d * D +
1 over two yeah uh remember we got to
get six 6 for three so 3 * 4 is 12 / 2
is 6 so it's uh D * D + 1 /
2 what we're not going to use this I
just wanted to uh do a little bit of
uh uh
combinatorics but now this one Matrix
like that for each entry M how many
possibilities does m take
on D so the answer is D ^2 * D +
1 uh constant C that I can play with I
haven't chosen them yet we're going to
think of is unknowns in a minute Unknown
Subject to a condition
now when I construct the metric in terms
of Y how do we do that we transform from
y to X we transform from y
tox and we'll get a metric starting with
gmn of
X we will get a new metric which we can
now
call G well let's just continue to call
it
MN of Y it's not it's it's the new
metric in Y
coordinates okay I'm going to require of
the constants
C the
condition in other words I'm going to
try to choose the C coefficients here
so that the derivative of G with respect
to Y is equal to
zero how many unknowns are there and how
many equations are there when I write
this out this will just become an
equation given what gmn of X
is I'll Transform it I'm not going to go
through the whole business we're going
to transform G find G of Y that's going
to involve the constant C because
they'll enter into the coordinate
transformation and then I'll write down
the
equations that the derivative of G with
respect to Any Given direction of
zero those become equations for C how
many equations are there how many such
equations are there well there's a
symmetric
Matrix that's D * D + 1/ two but how
many such symmetric matrices are there
in other words it's exactly the same
number of components of this object
gmn with an index s is there R of this
object a thing with three indices with
two of them symmetric same thing here
three indices with two of them
symmetric these equations there are just
exactly the same number of these
equations as there are coefficients
C the conclusion is there's just exactly
enough equation equations so that you
can always find a coordinate
transformation which sets the first
derivatives of G equal to
zero so that's something you can always
do once you've done the first
derivatives if you start looking at the
higher derivatives there are just too
many of them if I wanted to write down
higher derivatives here there are too
many higher derivatives to allow you to
solve the equations so at most you can
set the first derivatives of G equal to
zero right supposing we've done
that supposing we've done that and we
found
coordinates where this is equal to
zero all right there are various things
we can say first of all the derivative
of gmn with respect to X is equal to
zero at that point but we can say a
little bit more we can also say that the
christop symbols at that point are equal
to zero why because the christopal
symbols what are those let me write them
down for you again 12
GRS derivative of
G uh SM
with respect to
xn plus derivative of
g
s n with respect to
XM minus the last one derivative of G
MN with respect to XS this is the
christopal
symbols and of course if I have
chosen the first derivatives of the if
I've chosen coordinates which get rid of
the first derivatives at the point at
the origin for example then at that
point the christopal symbols are also
zero they're made up out of these
derivatives so at the point in question
the single point in
question the origin for example doesn't
have to be the origin of coordinates but
at the specific point in question I have
succeeded in simultaneous ly finding
coordinates in which the derivative of G
is equal to0 and in which the christopal
symbols are equal to
Z from that it follows that the
covariant derivative of G is equal to
zero because the covariant derivative of
G is just the derivative of
G with respect to X Plus christopal
symbol time G Plus another christopal
symbol time G one for each index of G I
won't bother writing the
details so once we have found
coordinates in which this is true and
which this is also equal to
zero we know that at that point at at
that point the covariant derivative of G
is equal to zero but on the other hand
the covariant derivative of G is a
tensor the ordinary derivative of G is
not not a tensor the christopal symbols
are not tensors but the covariant
derivative of G that's that was the
whole purpose of inventing covariant
derivatives to make things which really
are tensors so the covariant derivative
of G is equal to zero it's a tensor and
if a tensor is equal to zero in one
coordinate system then it's equal to
zero in every coordinate
system well there was nothing special
about the origin of coordinates I could
have done exactly the same thing at
every
point and so I conclude that the
covariant derivative of G is zero
everywhere just because I can choose
coordinates at any point where the
derivative of G and and the christopal
symbols are equal to
zero so that's the theorem
how how do we know that the the C's will
uh when we make them be non-constant
from point to point will this we just We
Begin by doing this at a point right but
now now now we are able to extend that
to say through a curve or something well
you can't know you got to go if you go
to a new Point there'll be new
C's if you go to another point the
function is
going those won't necessarily be
continuous would they they'll be
continuous yeah well the function c will
be continuous but they will vary from
point to
point the argument is a little circular
you use you use
that theant D of G being zero to derive
the
form that you know that's true that's
true the argument is a little bit
circular the argument is a little bit
circular uh but what it proves is the
consistency of the definitions if you
like you could introduce other kinds of
geometric structures where the
christopal symbols are replaced by other
objects there are other definitions of
um of the crustal symbols where the
covariant derivative of G for example is
not equal to zero such things are
possible uh I guess what we really prove
here is the consistency of the idea that
the covariant derivative of G is equal
to zero we assume the covariant
derivative of G is equal Z we calculate
from that the definition of the
christopal symbols and then we go back
and we discover with that definition the
covariant derivative of G is equal to
zero so actually you're right the the
definition is
circular not not not completely circular
you got sufficient conditions yeah for
something yeah yeah yeah uh in any case
the definitions are
consistent and they are the standard
definitions of how you covariant
differentiate the tensors to get tensors
question yeah if this is related to an
intuitive notion of
flatness what would happen if if somehow
or another like you had a wiggle and
then inside of every wiggle you put
another wiggle inside of every wiggle so
is there a constraint on G such that you
can't get a situation that is sort of uh
infinitely wiggly so you could never
find a coordinate system that would be
flat
yeah you're asking for
example whether G could be such an
unpleasant
function
that um its derivatives don't exist or
aren't continuous or something like that
so yes so the usual
assumption is that the G's are
continuous and differentiable everywhere
Just One S
let's say just
once
um and there will be exceptions for
example exceptions are places where the
geometries become
singular there will be exceptions but uh
in general a place where the geometry
becomes singular I'll tell you what
Singularity means in a second I give
I've given you examples of polar
coordinate singularities which are funny
right at the
origin right polar coordinate
singularities uh are not well sorry
polar coordinates are singular at the
origin that's
because at the origin you can't you
can't uh give a well-defined angular
coordinate to a
point uh it can happen that you choose
coordinates that are defined in a way
that make G's not be properly
differentiable or something but on the
other hand
you can also find other coordinates at
exactly the same point which are not
singular at that point so polar
coordinates are kind of bad coordinates
right at the origin but there's nothing
wrong or funny about the space at the
origin there it's not singular and the
way to prove it is just to go to other
coordinates where there is the where
where the metric is nice and uh
continuous and
differentiable there may be places
honest places where there's nothing
thing you can do to make the co to make
the metric differentiable and uh
friendly function at a point and if
that's the case then one says there's a
singularity a real physical Singularity
a real physical Singularity is a place
where there's nothing you can do not
only not to make the coordinates flat
but also to make them smooth to make the
um metric continuous and differentiable
at that point I'll give you an example
we're about to come through an example
now the cone the tip of the cone is a
real singularity in space where there is
no coordinate system that you can choose
which will make the metric at the tip of
the cone smooth there's something real
going on there and that's called a
singularity I will quick clarification
on the last term in the denominator of
the christopal symol oh yeah uh sorry
yeah
s is this when when you solve for the
see the constant is that like trying to
find system where
the yeah yeah yeah but you can do that
by making sure the derivatives of the
metric
vanish right this incidentally among
other things proves that the christopal
symbols can't be tensors
because by a coordinate transformation
you can make christopal symbols which
are not equal to zero equal to zero at a
particular point so the christopal
symbol is not a
tensor the derivative of a tensor is not
a tensor but combining together the
derivatives of tensors with christopal
symbols gives you tensors all right
so
good yeah so with this definition of the
christopal symbols it follows that the
covariant derivative of the metric is
zero
uh and whether it's a good thing or a
bad thing it's a true
thing now let's come to the idea of
curvature as I said curvature is a
mathematical
obstruction its presence prevents you
from finding coordinates in which the
space was
flat
uh and to understand curvature you first
have to understand something we've
already spent some time with the idea of
covariant derivative of a vector along a
curve let's go back we talked about this
uh previously but let me go back to
it that's the starting point
the notion of the covariant derivative
along a
curve the question I'll tell you what
question we want to answer we want to
answer a question like this supposing I
start with a vector somewhere in space
and I would like to move it to another
Point keeping it parallel to
itself in other words I would like to
move this Vector over to here and I
would like to know what its components
are over here if it's moved in a way
which keeps it parallel to
itself that's the notion of parallel
transport of a vector keeping it
parallel to itself as you move it we'd
like to move it over here now in flat
space it's pretty clear what you do you
just keep a vector parallel to itself
but when we are NE we can just choose a
cartisian coordinates cartisian
coordinates where the metric is just
Delta MN and in those coordinates
keeping the vector parallel to itself
just means keeping its coordinates
constant keeping its components constant
but if either we have curved coordinates
or a really curved space where we can't
choose the metric like this then we have
to find some definition of what it means
to move a vector parallel to itself it's
not clear that we can find such a
definition but I will tell you what it
is what a appropriate definition is all
right first of all take your
curve take your vector
and make the covariant derivative along
the curve I'll remind you what that is
if we have a
vector let's say it's a vector with
contravariant
indices then and it's defined All Along
The Curve All Along The Curve it's
defined it might even be defined in the
rest of space but I'm not interested in
in the rest of space just along the
curve then first of all we differentiate
the components with respect to distance
along the curve right d
s where s just represents distance along
the curve measured in in whatever units
we like right but this in itself is not
a true
Vector all right the Der the v's may
vary for reasons having nothing to do
with an actual physical variation of the
vector but having to do with variation
of the coordinates as you Move Along
what do you have to do to make a a
vector out of it you have to make the
covariant derivative which involves the
gamas Gamma New oh I'm using now the
notation of Relativity news and M's
instead of M and
n's uh it doesn't matter we could
somewhere I jumped into SpaceTime let's
do spaces that a space time
m m MN
[Music]
and
S let's say
no uh P let's call it P and then there
is a
v
n
DX P by
DS DX P by DS that's a vector remember
what this Vector is what is the name of
this
Vector DX by
DS that's the tangent Vector that's the
tangent Vector along the
curve and we worked out last time that
this is the covariant derivative of a
vector along a
curve along a curve it's the covariant
derivative where this is the tangent
vector
and this is the derivative of the vector
along the curve now I'll just remind you
we defined the geodesic Last Time by
saying this curve is a geodesic if the
covariant derivative of the tangent
Vector is
zero all right so let's just put that
down let's write that down the condition
for a
geodesic V now is going to be
replaced by DX XM by
DS in other words we going to replace V
by the tangent Vector itself and then
the derivative of a tangent Vector with
respect to S becomes a second derivative
DC XM by
DS2 plus gamma MN P now the tangent
Vector now V is the tangent Vector so
that's dxn by
DS and then dxp by DS
if the covariant derivative of the
tangent Vector is equal to zero if I'm
not saying it's always always true for
any curve but if the curve is chosen so
that the covariant derivative of the
tangent Vector is zero then the curve is
a geodesic in a sense it's the
straightest possible kind of curve that
you can have in the space
if it's flat space then the geodesics
are just straight lines if the space is
a sphere then the geodesics are great
circles in general they're nothing of
the sort they're curves that go through
the space but they're the straightest
possible curves they're the curves you
would get by just focusing and going
incrementally straight
ahead okay but now let's define
something else else let's define
parallel transport of a
vector supposing we have some Vector
which is not the tangent Vector now
let's come back to a general Vector like
this this Vector may not be the tangent
Vector here it is it's
V and it's allowed to vary along the
curve well if this covariant derivative
is equal to zero
then we say that that
Vector has been transported parallel to
itself along the curve in other words
this is as close as you can get to
saying the vector is constant along the
curve if its covariant derivative along
the curve is equal to zero one
says that this this Vector has been
parallell transported along the
curve okay can we always do that can we
always take a vector at this end and
parallel transport it in other words can
we take a vector at this end and now
move it along here in such a way that it
remains in this sense parallel to itself
yeah we
can let's just uh rewrite this slightly
differently let's just write this the
small change in VM
as we move from one point to another
let's get rid of the DS just multiply
through on both sides the small change
in VM is minus gamma
mnp
VN DX
P so if I have a small incremental
distance DX P
here oh sorry this should be a minus
sign right
not equal Z now
let's DVM all I've done is solve this
equation here multiply through by DS
that's not important and this tells me
how I should vary the components of VM
as I move along the curve so that so
that the covariant derivative is zero in
other words this tells me how to how to
move from one point to another it tells
me how to change V the component of V
given the components of V at a starting
point and the christofel symbols and the
little differential displacement DX it
tells me how to change V to the next
point in fact it tells me once I've
updated it from here to here I can do it
again and again and again and so it's
always
possible to choose the components of V
along the curve so that that the
covariant derivative is equal to zero
all you have to do is to solve for how
VM changes as you move along the curve
by knowing it at any one point you can
find out how it moves to the next point
and so forth so that's not hard that's
the uh that's the construction and the
definition of parallell transporting a
vector along a curve to Move It from one
place to
another you just change V
by an amount that's proportional to V
and that's proportional to the amount
that you're displacing it and is
proportional to the copel
symbols respect to parallel to
itself parallel to itself in other words
you have some curve in space I have a
vector and I want to move it along the
curve in space so that it always stays
parallel to
itself that's what we're trying to do
okay
just a little as side I always like the
Hot Wheels Hot Wheel car example if you
have a globe yeah and you and you move a
Hot Wheels car along it so that the
direction never changes you get the
great circle it's a or even on an inner
tube the Hot Wheels car is the thing
that always has the same direction and
it will give you the shortest distance
that'll give you geodesics yeah right
right but now we're taking a curve which
is not a geodesic first of all a geodes
IC is a curve is a vector which has been
moved parallel to itself no I just I was
just use that as an example as keeping
the same direction is the same as
minimizing distance that's for a
geodesic yeah but you can also parallel
transport something which is not a
geodesic for example we can parallel
sorry you can transport a vector which
is not the tangent
Vector I want to transport this Vector
along that line now if I take that
vector and transport it along that line
then the tangent Vector is the thing
that I'm transporting if the derivative
of the tangent Vector is zero it's a
straight line but I can also take any
Vector which is not necessarily a
tangent vector and start transporting it
it along the curve whether or not the
curve is a geodesic take any curve any
curve take a vector and transport it so
that it stays parallel to itself
that you can always do parallel to
itself and of the same
magnitude it would be this be the same
as saying that the angle between the
vector and the uh tangent Vector is
always constant no that's definitely not
what it says why because the tangent
Vector is itself changing Let's uh let's
do it a little differently here let's
take let's take a
circle and let's take a vector there's a
vector now I'm going to transport it
along
itself I'm going to transport it
parallel to itself I'm having trouble
keeping it exactly parallel but notice
by the time it gets down to here it's
become the tangent
Vector keeping it parallel to itself
along the circle will make it the
tangent Vector over here over here it's
perpendicular to the tangent vector and
up here it's the tangent Vector
again right so if I take a circle in
flat space a flat space Circle and
transport a vector parallel to itself
the angle relative to the curve
changes it's the
angle
relative to the neighbor which hasn't
changed the neighbor to this point or to
the vector over here is this point over
here it's relative to the neighboring
value that it has has n changed so we're
moving it along incrementally along the
curve crazy directions but always
keeping it parallel to its neighboring
value that's called parallel
transport Yeahs is any parameter SDS
could be any parameter WR the curve
right it's canceled out of this equation
here right right so there's a notion of
parallel transport along a curve
okay but now you could ask an
interesting
question
supposing does everybody understand what
it means it means as you move along the
curve even if the curve is turning you
make sure that the uh that the vector
stays parallel to itself let me give you
an example how you could do that uh
physically in in the real world a
gyroscope you take a gyroscope gyroscope
is a spinning object right if you don't
really forcibly change its direction and
you just hold it by its um uh tip or
whatever it is and you move it around it
will always face in the same direction
you don't have to move it along a
straight line you can move it along a
curve that gyroscope will transport
parallel to itself so a gyroscope is a
physical implementation of parallel
transport in space along a curve
okay you move it
around pay no attention to it just move
the tip of it and because of its angular
momentum it will continue to point in
the same direction even if you transport
it along the wildest wiggliest curve
right that's the idea of parallel
transport so this would be the equation
then that would govern in three
dimensions for example would govern the
components
of the axis of a gyroscope As you move
it
around now that's not the same as
cartisian coordinates relative to that
point though we haven't even introduced
any coordinates well we is
perpendicularity implied here what's
that is perpendicularity implied with
parallelism perpendicular to
what well in order to be parallel it
must be perpendicular to something
that's per cular to right yes yes so so
let me let me say it a different way
take two distinct vectors which happen
to be perpendicular to each other and
now parallel transport both of them they
will stay
perpendicular three vectors forming a t
a
Triad which you could make by three
perpendicular um gyroscopes and
transport them around and they'll stay
perpendicular to each other so parallel
transp report sort of preserves the
angles between vectors and so forth and
it's it's the closest thing that you can
have to the notion of moving a vector
around so that its direction and its
magnitude stay
fixed okay that's the notion of parallel
transport uh in fact it's possible to
prove that the magnitude of the vector
stays fixed but mostly I'm interested in
the direction now but now I come to a
funny
question how do I know
that if I parallel transport a vector
from one place to another along curve a
let's call that curve a I started over
here and I transport that gyroscope I
transport that gyroscope over here till
I get to here how do I know that if I
did it along a different
curve I would come to the same final
conclusion how do I know that if I
transport along a different curve it
wouldn't come out in some other
direction you have that equation no that
equation is just a definition of
parallel transport and it refers to a
curve how do I know if I choose another
if I chose another curve then in fact I
would get the same result well I'm just
saying you already canel BS so it
doesn't refer to a curve it does refer
to a curve the D X's here refer to the
curve the S is only the parameter along
the curve the DXs are the sequence of
little differentials along the curve
okay all right so this definition of
parallel
transport and in particular the idea of
transporting it all along a
curve we could ask does it
guarantee that the result of a parallel
transport leads to a unique Final Answer
independent of the curve connecting the
two
points well the answer is no it does not
guarantee that and in fact in general
it's not true if you par or you could
you could say the same thing another way
instead of parallel transporting it
along two different curves let's imagine
parallel transporting a curve uh sorry a
vector around a close
curve that's an even better situation
take the gyroscope and parall transport
it around the closed curve does it
necessarily come back to the same
direction okay the answer is in flat
space yes that's intuitively obvious the
bending of light around the star
well right but the question is in a
general space in a curved space Cas is
it necessarily true that if
incrementally from point to point you
make sure that you keep the vector
parallel to itself the gyroscope must
the gyroscope come back to itself and
the answer is
no
the obstruction or the fact or the the
condition the situation in which it
doesn't come back to itself is the
situation in which there is curvature
that's the diagnostic test to find out
if a space is flat or not is to
transport vectors around
curves and if you ever
find a curve that you can take the
vector around where the vector does not
come back to itself somewhere in there
is some curvature that's the definition
of curvature that parallel transport
around a closed curve does not bring you
back to the same Vector if there is
curvature it's quite obvious that you
cannot
uh flatten the space out to give it a
metric which looks like a conventional
flat space metric yeah does a mobus
strip have this
property sort of yeah let's see a Mobius
strip actually when you go around a
circle a vector can flip it's a flip
yeah yeah yeah but this this yes Mia
strip does have a kind of global I'll
call it Global curvature and I'll come
back to the miia strip in a minute Amia
strip is a non-orientable surface and so
it's a little bit peculiar but uh we can
certainly find examples without going to
non-orientable surfaces the cone is the
sort of simplest example of
all a cone is a space which is
by the cone everybody know what I mean
by a
cone like an ice cream
cone it's what you get if you take a
sheet of
paper cut out an angular
wedge all right there's an angular wedge
I wish I had a knife does anybody have a
scissor with
them h
yeah I I know I can do a I can do a
trick but let me uh what I do with the
cover to
this oh okay ah my
knees oh
cool
okay okay so let's cut
out the angular
wedge that's called an angular deficit
or an angle
deficit I should have brought a big
piece of uh what do we call that kind of
paper in kindergarten oak tag oak tag
yeah uh big piece of it
and cut it
out so you cut out a wedge like that and
then you sew it together along along the
wedge like that and you make a cone is
is that obviously a
cone yeah that's obviously a cone right
now once you sew it together that
way you could cut it and slice it some
other place and open it up so it doesn't
matter where you cut
it and open it up but wherever you cut
it and open it up it looks like that now
notice it looks pretty darn flat but
when you put it together like this it no
longer looks flat and in fact you can't
flatten it out not without smooshing it
and uh stretching it so the curve the
cone is a curved space but it's a curved
space of a very special type where
there's no curvature anywhere except at
the tip let's see if we can refine that
and uh and understand it so let's start
with a cone I'll first draw it as a
cone here's the tip up
here and of course a real mathematical
cone goes on and on forever it doesn't
terminate at this point over here but we
can terminate it because I can't draw it
forever and then we come with our
scissors I don't think I need this
anymore but let's leave it here I might
want to do some more we cut
it open it
up and it looks
like I guess like
um with slice paper what's that with a
slice yeah a pie with a uh slice taken
out all right so that's a cone with a
rule the rule is that point over here is
identified with a point over here for
example if a fly walks around across
here and crosses the red line then in
this map over here think of this as a
map of the cone the fly walks around
over here and then jumps jumps over to
here the red
line has been sliced
open but then we have to remember to
identify
points in the appropriate way that
that's a mathematical construction of a
cone in terms of a flat space now notice
that this sheet of paper as well as this
drawing over here is completely flat
everywhere's along here uh as long as we
keep away from the problematic areas
we've cut it and the tip of the cone
over here it's completely flat so first
of all let's take a closed curve over
here that's a closed
curve on this flat sheet of paper and
now take our gyroscope and transport it
around taking the gyroscope and
transporting it around the closed curve
parallel to itself at every
Point all right so
whoever is doing this parallel
transporting as he moves it he makes
sure that incrementally it stays in the
same direction and as he goes all the
ways around guess what what happens to
it it comes back to
itself all right so there's an example
of a parallel transport around the
closed curve where the vector did come
back to its original value but now let's
parallel trans Port around the tip of
the
cone all right so now we're going to
take a curve that circumnavigates the
tip of the
cone all right and in particular let's
start with a
vector just uh for just for the sake of
clarity I think I find it a little
clearer let's start with the vector
being aligned
along the red
line and let's parallel transport along
along the curve all right first of all
the curve on here looks like that it's a
circle it's a piece of a circle when we
open it
up and the vector starts out in this
direction
whoops starts out by assumption along
the red
line now we move it parallel to itself
parallel to itself does not mean that we
move it so that it's pointing radially
out that's not parallel to itself
parallel to itself means we keep its
direction
fixed and by the time we get over to
here it's now
pointing in this case practically
perpendicular to the red line what's
going to happen supposing we now close
this up we might slice it along some new
place we might slice it along a new
place and close it up over here so that
we close it up back into the curve over
here look what it's done it's gone from
something which is parallel to the red
line to something no longer parallel to
the red line and that means when we
parallel transport it around it's going
to come back to some new Vector which is
going to
be
perpendicular or not perpendicular but
at some
angle relative to the original Vector in
other words it's clear When I close this
up this Vector will wind up coming out
in this direction just think about
closing this
up and this Vector over here will wind
up pointing in some new Direction so
here's an example of parallel
transporting a vector at every stage
keeping it parallel to itself and by the
time it goes around a closed curve it's
not paral it's not parallel to uh to the
starting point
only notice that only happens if we go
around the
tip if we steer clear of the tip that
doesn't
happen
Okay uh the tip is the point at which
there is
curvature all right so the tip the the
diagnostic
test has I don't know whether we should
say it failed or it succeeded it's
failed to demonstrate that the space is
flat it has succeeded in finding a point
of curvature why do I say a point of
curvature because if I circumnavigate
any other
point I find no shift in the direction
but only but every circum navigation of
this point gives me the same angular
shift so what does it
do the presence of this point of
curvature has the effect of rot ating
vectors which have been parallel
transported around in a closed curve it
doesn't matter that this closed curve is
a circle it could be any closed
curve around uh around the tip it will
always rotate the
vector by the same angle incidentally if
we started with a
vector if we started with a vector which
was not along the red axis but some
other direction and we went around again
it would still come out uh in some new
Direction and how about this angle the
angle that the vector gets rotated how
much is
that that depends on this angle
here this is called the angular deficit
here it's the amount that was bit out of
the pi let's call it Theta when you take
a vector around this closed path it gets
rotated by the same angle
Theta so one might say that there's an
amount of curvature which is
parameterized by the angle
Theta the bigger Theta is or is it uh
yeah if Theta is a very small angle in
other words if it's just a very very
tiny piece of Pi were taken out then
there's very very little change in the
direction of the vector that's been
parallel
transported uh the bigger that the angle
Theta is the more rotation there is in
this
Vector so that's an example of a point
of
curvature now let me point something out
that here we are we're going to parallel
transport around this particular
curve nothing can depend
on whether the tip of this cone here was
truly pointed or whether I came along
with my sandpapering machine and uh and
whittled off and made it uh
smooth okay so
somehow the
um effect of going around this
curve is the same whether this has been
smoothed or not however ever supposing I
go around the curve very close to the
top here then I'll get a different
answer than on the
cone then I'll get a different answer uh
in fact I'll get a much smaller angle at
the top of the cone here than if I go
around
here okay so somehow this operation of
going around this particular curve has
located the fact that there's some
curvature in there but it hasn't told me
the detail
this particular curve has not diagnosed
whether there was a point of curvature
here or whether there was a smooth
curvature there but it's told me there
is some curvature in there because when
I go around the curve well because when
I go around the Clos curve I don't come
back to it to
itself
so uh let's see now oh let's do a sphere
let's do a sphere a sphere is also
curved
question yeah when you say parallel
transported can you nail that down a bit
more
no because if that's the angle to the
circle going around then that basically
defeats the
argument it's not it's not radially out
I can understand why it's not radially
out if it's Point towards at Infinity
then again the AR we take the curve and
we break it up into lot of little
straight lines
okay and then we parallel transport from
one to the
other and I'm not sure how to say this
right we're not transporting the vector
so that it stays at the same angle to
the curve with transporting so it stays
the same angle to
itself but if it's a geodesic does it
stay at the same angle to the tangent
right
I have a question so that that that I
think that helps answer that question
because in a sense parallel trans if if
that's constant Direction then parallel
transport is constant with respect to
the constant Direction that's right if
you parallel transport something along a
geodesic it will stay at the same angle
gesc at least in two dimensions three
dimensions gets a little more
complicated because a vector can twist
around so there's something called
torsion where the vector can twist
around but at least this in two
Dimensions that if you transport a
vector on a
geodesic then uh it will stay at the
same angle to the
[Music]
curve on a cone that would be sort of
spal on on a cone geodesic would look
like a spiral it wouldn't be just a
circle cut perpendicular to the AIS uh
the
geodesics the geodesics on a cone
are simply the geodesics that it
inherits from Flat space okay uh so
straight lines in here are geodesics uh
on the
cone
um
yeah well they
will they'll get curved when you curve
curl it right say it again they'll get
curved when you curl them
up well uh when you uh
you see the straight lines on here
they're
geodesics also the straight line here is
a geodesic the straight line here is a
geodesic I don't know would you say they
get curved when you uh yeah sort of if
you're looking at it from the top they
appear to get curve the yeah the point
is what happens when a straight line
crosses the
identified when the straight line
crosses where the lines that are were
identified they is no longer look
straight unless it actually has okay an
ANG right right what you do if you're
interested in the geodesic which crosses
here then what you do that's like a
geodesic which crosses from here to here
then the thing to do is to close it up
over
here and um this is going to be hard
and I don't want it to fall apart
and open it up over
there okay it's the same
space and now the geodesic that goes
across the original thing can be
drawn all right and you're right what
will happen is that when I open it up
again that geodesic which went across
here will look
bent the geodesic which crosses across
here
will look bent but when I close it up
again it'll look
straight okay so there is a geodesic for
example which connects this point to
this
point it doesn't go around here it goes
across here and then changes angle and
goes over here that angle would be
repeated on the slice you made on the
other side to make it parall yeah for
example if the if the angle was 90° over
here then it'll be 90° over here what
I'm saying is once you close that up by
making the other slit angle becomes the
same absolutely absolutely but this
curve from here to here will then become
a smooth straight line
right so if you're interested in curves
that go from here to here the thing to
do is not to use this representation but
close it up over here and open it up
somewhere else and you can always do
that so cutting and pasting is the way
to think about cones
uh so we do see that there are
situations where parallel transport
along a closed curve does not bring you
back to the same thing and when you
don't come back to the same thing under
such
circumstances that is the diagnosis of
curvature somewhere in the
geometry usually I mean in typically it
means that this curvature somewhere is
inside that curve somewhere is in the
interior of that curve uh curvature in
higher Dimensions is a little more
complicated we'll come to
it but uh let's just do a sphere for a
moment let's take uh the
hemisphere I'm interested in the sphere
but I just want to draw a hemisphere for
the moment and now I want to parallel
transport a vector
around not a great circle but some other
Circle a great circle is a geodesic
a great circle great circle being for
example the Equator so transporting
parallel transporting a vector along a
great
circle uh just means keeping the angle
relative to the great circle fixed but
that's not true of a curve which is not
a great
circle parallel transporting is a little
more complicated and here's a simple way
to think about it think about the bug
moving along here carrying his little
gyroscope with him can that bug who can
only see an infinitesimal little
distance around him can he tell he or
she can he or she tell that this curve
was not a curve whoops on a
cone a cone which has been fit so that
its tangent to the sphere can everybody
visualize that cone yeah I don't think
you can you just said so right it's a
Dun cap it's a Dun cap on a on a
spherical head and it just happens to be
tangent right along that uh that curve
what's going to happen when I transport
parallell a vector around there it's
going to do exactly the same thing as it
would have done on the corresponding
cone okay okay how big is the angle
deficit of the cone well that depends on
where I draw this
curve for example if I draw the curve up
here the angle deficit there'll be less
of an angle deficit it'll be a flatter
cone it'll be more like
this in fact if I make
the circle a very small one way way up
close to the North
Pole then that cone is practically a
flat cone with a very very small angular
deficit so the answer is if I take a
vector around the North
Pole staying very close to the North
Pole transported around the angle May
deviate a tiny bit but not very much if
I take it around at 45° here it'll
you'll discover a fairly large angular
deficit and so but in any case the point
is that the sphere is curved we've
diagnosed the curve the sphere by
transporting vectors or parallel to
themselves along closed curves and found
out that they don't come back to
themselves not surprisingly that means
that this curvature on the sphere that
the sphere is a curved surface it also
means that you cannot find flat
coordinates you know Delta Mu new type
coordinates on the flat sphere so
curvature is the obstruction to
flattening a geometry out and making it
everywhere
flat
uh I'll tell
you the fact now that if you have a
curved
geometry and you go around a small curve
a small curve then of
course the angle deficit is
small okay so if you take in any
geometry as long as you take a small
enough curve and you take a vector and
parallel transport it around the
deviation of the direction will turn out
to be small you can see that on the
sphere here that uh that up near the
North Pole of the sphere the
corresponding cone has a very small
small angular
deficit how much of an how much of an
angle how much of a rotation do you
think
occurs for a
given Circle up
here is the
angle here proportional to the
distance or
what anybody know area the area the area
right this is something that's worth
working out you can work this out by
yourself it's just a question of taking
a small circle up here fitting it to a
cone all that means is you have here's
your
circle you uh here you have your two
points that correspond to the circle and
um draw the tangent
vectors how much of an angle is involved
the angle will be proportional to the
area of that little
region so it's the area that controls
how much of a uh how much of a deficit
or how much of a um a displacement you
get when you go around a small circle or
a small curve yeah even if the area is
not circular even if it's not a circle
the uh the displacement and angle will
be proportional to the area all right so
we can write down let's call it Delta
Theta well let's yes let's just call it
Delta Theta the angle that the
vector uh fails to reproduce the
original direction that Delta Theta will
be
proportional to the area of the enclosed
curve times something a
number and that number number is called
the curvature
R for example if I have a very big
sphere and I take the same little area
over here I'll get a very small angular
deficit on the other hand if I take a
small
sphere and take the same Ang uh the same
size circle over here I'll get a rather
large angular deficit the smaller the
geometry the bigger the
curvature the smaller the geometry the
bigger the
curvature
that's call that's the curvature of a
two-dimensional surface is the
relationship between the area of small
little
curves and the angular let's just call
it the angle deficit that's suffered
when you go around the curve yeah the
area here the area on the surface or the
area of the uh project well it really
doesn't matter because we're talking
about yeah we should be talking only
about very small areas so let's call
this Delta area in other words the right
thing to say is that for an
infinitesimal area you get an
infinitesimal angle and the coefficient
is called the curvature and it doesn't
matter in detail what the shape of the
curve is that's something you need to
prove but it's a true statement yeah in
the case of the chical example vectors
that we're talking about must lie on the
surface of the cone it's a two-
dimensional space correct in the case of
the three-dimensional sphere is that
also no the surface of the sphere is two
dimensional the vectors are do not lie
on the surface of the sphere do not have
to line on the surface of the SP you can
think that that that is a good question
you don't usually think of vectors as
lying in the space you usually just
think of the vectors as having a
magnitude and having a
direction uh so you can think of the
vectors as sort of lying in the tangent
space to the to the surface the vectors
you don't don't think of the vectors as
being creatures which live on the
surface they're creatures which have a
direction and a
magnitude uh and they point along the
surface but they don't stick to the
surface when the surface uh changes so
you think of them as things which live
in the tangent
space okay that's the official words but
yes you're right I mean uh the vectors
don't really literally exist in the
space itself they the mathematical
objects which live in the tangent
space if you go around the equator and
tangent Vector that's going to work just
fine and yet there's an area deficit
there isn't yeah but that's this this
formula is is only for small areas for
large areas uh you have to work it out
in general some integral to do and
that's right
uh uh now somebody asked me about the
meia script the meia script is a funny
thing how do you define AIA
strip you define AIA Strip by taking a
strip like that
and then making
identifications that this point over
here is equivalent to this point a
a this point over here is equivalent to
this point
BB the the vector from or the segment
from A to B is equivalent to the segment
over here from A to B but quite clearly
that means if you take a vector around
the meia strip it changes is it flips
its
direction so that's a an example of a
kind of curvature but meia strips are so
weird that they don't fall into the uh
into the same classification they
nonorientable surfaces and uh you're
call what is it you're calling it that's
in in my language it's called a Mobius
band and and you're calling it strip not
just neither it's
VI okay okay it's pronunciation same
word different
pronunciation
VI forgive me for being
American excuse me well it's it's meus
in the same sense that aeba is is it I
don't know no no it's m I believe you m
o e b ba a right
amiba wait a second was a
person no no I'm just saying that that
it's anglicized
to right right right
right raises a question about the Taurus
the Taurus good right because that's
also rectangle
identifications right so the
mathematically idealized taus which is
made in the way you just said is
flat is strictly flat when the Taurus is
defined in the way that you said which
is a rectangle with identifications
across the rectangle a real Taurus like
the bagel the surface of a bagel is
curved uh but it has an integrated
curvature which is zero we'll come to
that well maybe we'll come to it uh the
uh the problem is you can't construct a
flat Taurus in three-dimensional space
you can do it in four-dimensional space
you can't embed it in three-dimensional
space
uh actually you can I just realized you
can not so it's in well it's
intrinsically flat but you can't get a
flat edding yeah I'm going to make a
flat edding for
you all right here's the rectangle what
we want to do is identify this edge with
this Edge and this edge with this Edge
some people don't know what I'm talking
about so I'll explain it a Taurus is the
surface of a bagel or
donut and it looks like that just think
of the surface we're not thinking about
the interior not the good stuff that you
eat but just the uh the surface and now
cut it cut it open over
here and open it up what does it become
it becomes a piece of a cylinder right I
mean just uh
topologically it has has the properties
of a piece of a
cylinder and now when you've done that
cut it along here cut it along here and
open it up and what does it become it
becomes a
rectangle it becomes a rectangle this
Edge over here is identified with this
Edge so that means this Edge over here A
B C D becomes a b c d a fly which walks
across from from here to here walks
across here and reappears over
here and the bottom a b c is identified
with a top
ABC okay that's a Taurus and clearly
that Taurus can be drawn on the
Blackboard so that it is
flat uh normally when you draw a Taurus
it's curved over here at this edge here
it almost looks like a sphere so it must
be curved over here in the in side over
here it has negative curvature on the
outside it has positive curvature so far
we haven't defined the sign of the
curvature but you know question can you
um can you take
this sheet of
paper and fold it together so that it
forms a Taurus well yeah you actually
can you fold it
together you got to put a fold in it all
right now this
Edge this Edge has been identified with
this Edge I could take a piece of tape
and fold it now I want to identify this
edge with this Edge so I fold it again
like that I don't even need to fold it I
just do this and now think of a bug
walking around the bug walks around from
here comes out on this side comes around
over here comes out on this side so
that's going around the Taurus this way
or can go around this way that's going
around the Taurus this way so so in fact
I can make a flat to it's just a little
bit you have you have a not much
nourishment in it kind of curv there on
the edges right well actually there is
no integrated curvature on the
edge no the goes
like it's got a little bit of positive
curvature on one side a little bit of
negative curvature on the other side
yeah uh so it's a little bit degenerate
as you say and um uh but in dimensions
in four dimensions you can draw a
surface a two-dimensional
surface that is an absolutely flat
Taurus so a
Taurus can be
flattened a sphere cannot be
flattened
uh interesting
difference
and
um
yeah now notice what we're do
but the constant I mean if you draw
small circles at various place on
tourist you get either deficit in
Surplus as you go
around are you asking me about positive
and negative curvature I'm asking you if
Delta Thal R Delta
a what this what what what values do you
get from R you don't always get zero on
a flat plain zero no but on the Taurus
Oh no that's on a real taurus meaning
one which is embedded in three
dimensions there's curvature all over it
get R different values different values
and in particular on the outside of the
Taurus I'm going to explain now the sign
of the curvature and then we'll come
back to and I'll tell you about the
Taurus okay there's a notion of the sign
of the curvature and here's the way it
works uh uh look down from the top and
let's go around uh
clockwise or counterclockwise either
way uh let's see we're going to go
around this around this cone around the
cone oh
incidentally in the case of the cone
what is the curvature how much curvature
what is the numerical value of the
curvature the numerical value of the
curvature is zero everywhere except at
the tip and the curvature at the tip is
angle no it's infinite it's infinite
because the curvature is the ratio of
the angle deficit to the area and I can
take an infinitely small area and still
find that angle deficit so the curvature
at the tip of the cone is actually
infinite it's an example of infinite
curvature infinite curvature means a
singularity in the geometry a place
where it it's not smooth Okay so so we
have the idea of curvature but now what
about the sign of the curvature so let's
take a vector let's say pointing
perpendicular Let's uh amuse ourselves
by taking a perpendicular vector and
parall transporting it around to here by
the time it gets over to here it will be
pointing in the same direction be sort
of pointing this
way parallel to itself and now close up
the
angle close up the angle and which way
is it pointing after you close up the
angle it's pointing kind of this way
right all right we've transported the
vector in the counterclockwise Direction
we've transported it counterclockwise
and which way did it
rotate same same way rotated the same
way and so we could give signs to these
things we could say that
um
that going around this circle in the
counterclockwise Direction Let's Define
that to be a positive little area let's
imagine now that areas can have signs
here's the way we assign a sign to an
area if we have a little area and we go
around it counterclockwise we call that
area positive if we go around it the
other way we call it
negative so areas are things which have
a sign you don't usually think of an
area as having a sign but think of the
area as having a sign because it's not
just an area it's an area plus an
oriented
boundary there's a sense of we're
imagining a sense of direction around
the
boundary for counterclockwise let's call
it positive for clockwise let's call it
negative
then
on the sphere here or on the cone if we
go around clockwise Delta Theta is also
clockwise and that corresponds to
positive
curvature since Delta Theta and Delta
area have the same sign in other words
if we go around the area
clockwise we transport around a curve
which goes around clockwise Delta Theta
was also clockwise that's positive
curvature is there such a thing is
negative
curvature and the answer is yes it's not
hard to manufacture geometries which
have negative
curvature it's a little harder to see
not nearly as easy to
see but if you take a saddle shape
the uh you know a mountain
pass is it clear what shape that is
Pringles potato chip what's that
Pringles potato chip yeah potato chip
right
exactly uh that's
right a pringle is it Pringles yeah ones
mold they aren't truly they're they're
bad no let's take uh kettle's potato
chips or something the good some good
one yeah that's right the potato chip or
the saddle surface the saddle surface
has the property believe it or not that
if you go around the closed curve
clockwise around the closed curve the
transported Vector rotates in the
opposite
direction right um here's the way here's
the way you can think about negatively
curved
surfaces in
particular we made a
positive curvature
Singularity by cutting out a piece of
the pie
right I'm going to show you how to make
a negative curve and you go home and do
this and prove to yourself that what
happens is what I say
happens we're going to make a
[Music]
cut and now instead of cutting out a
wedge we're going to add something we're
going to add an extra angular piece
in an angle excess instead of an angle
deficit here's the way we do
it all right here's our angle
excess right here I take my Surface I
open it up notice it gets kind of
floppy and stick the angle excess in
and now tape it along here and tape it
along here and I have now instead of an
angle can everybody see
it instead of an angle a piece of angle
missing it has more than
360° going instead of having less than
360° going around it has more than 360°
going
around doing that makes a piece of
negative curvature if you transport a
vector around that
you'll find out that if you transport
cter clockwise the vector rotates
clockwise that's a surface of negative
curvature so negative curvature and
positive curvature both exist negative
curvature is a little bit less intuitive
because it doesn't involve things like
spheres but rather things like I don't
know how to describe them I'm not sure
the H say it again the inner surface it
is the inner surface of the Taurus
absolutely that's what I was going to
come to right it is the inner surface of
the Taurus so the outer surface of the
Taurus but the outer surface I don't
what I mean I don't mean looking at the
Taurus from the uh from the D I mean the
outer surface is the part around here
the inner surface of the Taurus is that
part the inner surface is more saddle
shaped the outer surface is more sphere
shaped you'll discover that the outer
parts of the Taurus in other words the
boundary out here is positively curved
the portion in near the whole lay is
negatively curved and the total
integrated curvature if I integrate the
curvature what does integrating the
curvature do forg get it not important
right now but there's as much positive
curvature as there is negative curvature
on the Taurus on the other hand the
sphere is everywhere as positively
curved okay so we now have the basic
idea in two dimensions of what curvature
means and the most important thing for
us is that curvature is an obstruction
to flattening the geometry flattening
the geometry by definition means finding
coordinates where the metric is just
Delta
muu all of these words are exactly the
same in space
time they exactly the same there are
Curves in SpaceTime you can take closed
Curves in SpaceTime you can transport
vectors by exactly the same rules the
rule being right
here the christopal symbols are
constructed from the metric in exactly
the same way and the notion of curvature
SpaceTime curvature is the same and as
the notion of just spatial curvature it
is harder to visualize
it's much harder to divis visualize the
geometry of SpaceTime than it is of just
ordinary space we weren't equipped with
the mental architecture to visualize
SpaceTime but the rules are essentially
the
same so a curved SpaceTime is one if you
like where when you go around closed
paths trying to keep a four Vector A
Spacetime Vector parallel to itself you
won't be able to because there curvature
in the middle
um we're going to Define next time the
curvature
tensor but the basic idea of general
relativity is first of all that
SpaceTime is
curved and second of all the curvature
is due to masses is due to mass or more
generally energy and
momentum eal mc^2 of course is the equ
equality or the equivalence between
energy and
mass energy and mass are the same thing
except for a conversion factor the
square root of the square of the speed
of
light uh energy and momentum we'll find
out come together but energy and
momentum are the things which create
curvature that's the analog of the
statement that mass creates
gravitational field and gravitational
field that cannot be removed by a
coordinate
transformation gravitational field that
cannot be removed by going to an
accelerated frame of
reference that's the presence of a chunk
of mass it's an obstruction they getting
rid of the gravitational field energy
and momentum create curvature curvature
is also an obstruction to get getting
rid of the curvature of SpaceTime so
that's the Bas basic theme we're going
to write down if not derive the
equations relating the curvature of
space time to the presence of energy and
momentum and then we're going to talk
about how particles
move in a curved SpaceTime and the
answer is they move along geodesics so
we're going to do here's the here's the
goal start with some energy and momentum
some Mass C calculate the curvature
around it and then that gives us a set
of geodesics and what we're going to
want to see is that those geodesics
behave almost identically to the way
Newtonian trajectories move around a
mass in Newtonian
gravity of course we're going to do a
little better than that we're going to
see that there are some corrections to
Newton but that's the goal uh curvature
is like gravitational field it's created
by man
Solutions of fals ma are essentially
just geodesics in SpaceTime that's the
uh that's the goal for the next couple
of lectures and then we'll try to study
some particular examples in particular
the um uh the Schwarz Shield geometry of
a chunk of
mass and I think uh I'm not sure where
we'll go after that any questions
absolutely
none space embedded in another space
said they said the upper space the
higher space is flat then is parel
transport in the upper the higher
dimensional space well okay so let's see
so um
uh no not no no no parallel transport is
not defined by be staying parallel in
the embedding
space yeah
um let's put it this way take
three-dimensional space and now make a
curved surface in it if the rule for
parallel transport was to keep the
vector parallel in the three-dimensional
sense then when you went around any curv
there would be no such thing as
curvature no no but you keep a c in
Project Pro okay when you parallel
transport a vector in the two
dimensional space you keep it in the
two-dimensional space it's always
pointing in the two-dimensional
space
uh yeah you can probably think of yeah
um you can understand it better if you
think that for it to be a vector it has
to be just two numbers it cannot be
three numbers that's right that's right
but let me give you another way to think
about it um as we said we can always
find coordinates at a
point which
are Delta
MN all right that means that the
coordinate axes locally at that point
are perpendicular to each other and in
fact they're as straight as
possible parallel transport from one
point to another point in the vicinity
of this point where we've made the
metric look like this
is just keeping the components of the
metric sorry the components of the
vector fixed transporting it as if space
was flat the problem is that when you go
over to
here the original coordinates
here for which the metric was just Delta
MN are no longer the coordinates at this
point where the metric is Delta MN
there's a little bit of shift of
coordinates to keep them uh to the new
coordinate system and so it you well
okay um it's a little more
complicated anyway um familiarize
yourself as much as you can with the
idea of parallel
transport and the next time we will
Define the curvature tensor and again
the curvature tensor is always related
to what happens to a vector when you
when you parall transport it around the
curve it's more complicated in three
dimensions why because the curve could
be
oriented along any
plane and furthermore the rotation of
the vector could be a rotation about any
axis in four dimensions it's even more
complicated but the basic idea is go
around a little curve oriented along
some plane and see how the vector
rotates in space or in space time and
that rotation of the vector when you go
around the little circle that is what
defines curvature that's the notion of
remani and curvature and it's the notion
that uh that's at the heart of the
gravitational field
[Music]
okay the proceeding program is
copyrighted by Stanford University
please visit us at stanford.edu